[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, today's sutta is Sankhyātā 47.20, the beauty of the land, or the most beautiful woman in the land.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thus I have heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: At one time, the Blessed One was staying among Sumbas in a market town of Sumbas named Sedaka.
[SPEAKER_00]: There, He addressed the monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as monks, if people were together, saying the beauty of the land, the beauty of the land, a great crowd would assemble.
[SPEAKER_00]: That beauty of the land is the most skilled in dancing, most skilled in singing.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that beauty of the land dances and sings, monks, an even larger crowd would gather to watch her.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then a man would come, desiring to live, not to die, desiring happiness and averse to pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if someone were to say to him, Now, good man, this full oil bowl must be carried by you between the great crowd and that beautiful woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a man with raised sword will follow you right behind you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever you spill even a little bit of oil, your head will be cut off.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you think, monks?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would that man not attend to the oil bowl and allow negligence outwardly?
[SPEAKER_00]: And here I added passages from the Agama, Sangita Agama Parallel, which kind of adds a bit more description.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in Agama it says, what do you think, monks?
[SPEAKER_00]: That man holding the oil bowl, could he fail to keep in mind the oil bowl?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fail to keep in mind the killer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the monks obviously replied, well, surely not, Venerable Sir.
[SPEAKER_00]: In Āgama, they said,
[SPEAKER_00]: This simile, monks, has been made to convey a meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the meaning is, the full bowl, oil bowl, monks, is the term for recollectedness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Āgama says, adds to this, saying, if there is a śramaṇa or brāhmaṇa correct in the body and self-respecting,
[SPEAKER_00]: Unifying his mind and thoughts, not giving attention to the sounds and forms, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: sense objects, while collecting all mental phenomena, dwelling in the recollectedness of the body, that one is my disciple, one who follows my teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the Buddha continues saying, therefore, monks, you should train.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollectedness of the body will be developed by us, made much of, made our vehicle, our foundation, established, accumulated and well undertaken.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, indeed, monks, you should train.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is where the Pali Sutta ends, but then the Agama has quite a bit more, including some interesting verses at the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Agama continues saying, what is called monks, a monk who is correct in the body, self-respecting, unifying his mind and thoughts, not giving attention to the sounds and forms, eyes and objects, while collecting all mental phenomena and dwelling in the recollectiveness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's a monk who is recollecting body within the body, feeling within the feeling, citta within citta, dhamma within dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a monk who practices the satipaṭṭhāna with diligent effort, right understanding and right recollectedness, subduing worldly craving and sorrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is called the monk that is correcting the body, self-respecting, unifying his mind and thoughts and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: He repeats it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the Buddha said that, he immediately followed with a verse saying, Unifying mind with right recollectness, protect and uphold the old bowl.
[SPEAKER_00]: Guard one's own mind accordingly in a place not yet reached.
[SPEAKER_00]: Extremely difficult to pass through, superior and subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: What all Buddhas have spoken, the doctrine of a sharp sword, one should unify one's mind, diligently guard and uphold it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No such ordinary man, in the matters of negligence, can enter such a state, the teaching of non-negligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha having spoken the discus, monks rejoiced and practiced accordingly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a short sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll go back to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, the obvious points, you know, they come up when you look at this sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I remember even, like, when I was, like, a long time ago, when I started practicing, when I was a layman,
[SPEAKER_00]: When I came across this sutta, and as I said before, usually most of us would have kind of arrived at Buddhism and the dhamma and the suttas through some interest or idea of meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: The concentration practices or whatever, whatever vague ideas we all would have started with, that was kind of our framework that they then eventually, through circumstances or who knows what else, kind of directed us towards the suttas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem with that was that even when the suttas were being read back then,
[SPEAKER_00]: You would have been reading them, I know I did, through the same kind of framework and ideas of concentration practices, focus and meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I remember when I read this sutta, it was kind of like, aha, okay, so you must focus on the on the bowl on your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you must like really really kind of intently concentrate on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you survive.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you don't spill it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm pretty sure in Theravāda it's often used, that sutta, to support the ideas of focusing practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think also in Goenka, as well, it's been singled out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then I remember thinking, it's like, yeah, but hold on, if you actually stop and think about it, if you were to have something on top of your head and
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to walk through a crowd or even just do it as a test.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just walk through your room, cluttered room with chairs and stuff and people around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, would you be concentrating on the thing on your head?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, would I be needing to concentrate on the ball on top of my head?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, no, because it's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's known.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's felt there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to, like, double down in my ways of attending to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to, like, not spill it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already felt quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: I shouldn't be concentrating on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I should actually be more aware of the broader sense of balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: More aware of the broader sense of my environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: More aware of where I'm heading, where I'm going.
[SPEAKER_00]: As opposed to just shut that all out and just focus hard on the sensations of the top of my head where the ball touches my skin or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not just that that practically wouldn't work if you were to try it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, oh, that's why the Sutta goes into this elaborate description of the most beautiful woman in the world with the most beautiful voice and the most beautiful dance and everybody from the country gathers.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like to create the environment
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, to show you the environment that you live in, which is the environment of sense objects, that are always enticing, that are always pressuring you to look, to taste, to touch, to think about, to choose, to act towards,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you have a ball on top of your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like, oh, so the sutta is really intentionally contrasting that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, just focus on the top of your head where the ball is and doesn't really matter what's around you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole point is you have to walk through the crowd.
[SPEAKER_00]: The crowd that's not a neutral, indifferent crowd, the crowd of rowdy senses, objects, other people and so on, and you are the one who mustn't spill the oil from the bowl.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you try doing that through the practice of sensation watching or concentrating or whatever, nostrils of breathing, oh, you will spill it even before you reach the crowd.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in no time you'll bump into somebody or somebody will bump into you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the way you would actually have to practically walk through it, would be not losing the sense of balance, not losing the sense of the danger, most importantly, that there is a man with a drawn sword.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you won't forget about the ball on top of your head, unless you choose to go and do something else, and distract yourself with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you would choose to do something else and distract yourself with it, when you forget about the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the danger is there, the awareness, the recollectedness, the non-forgetfulness of that ball will be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, what you're actually paying attention to is where you're going,
[SPEAKER_00]: What you're choosing to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you choosing to turn your head and look?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you choosing to stop and and start dancing yourself because it's just so amazing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that you will be paying attention to what you're doing, you will also be paying attention and trying to foresee what other people around you will do it that might affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can be as careful as you want walking through, but if you are taking the course in the crowd, where it's, like, where men are even rowdier, even crazier, there is a good chance somebody will just bump into you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how careful you are, and you'll spill the oil, and your head will be cut off.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're foreseeing that, foreseeing that certain actions, although might not be necessarily unwholesome, like, well, going left or right makes no difference,
[SPEAKER_00]: Certain actions might actually take you in a worse environment, where you won't be able to protect your mind, in the same sense, if you would have avoided it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would be foreseeing the behavior and so on, where it's riskier, and then you wouldn't go that way, because of it, because... why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the danger of spilling the oil.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: That danger is what gives you the context to all your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you start thinking about it, you realize, as I said, the whole simile, the way, what it emphasizes, but even if you just practically
[SPEAKER_00]: Do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Put something on your head and try walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will realize, oh, so it's actually about contrasting that kind of discrepancy of the senses pulling you and what you have to maintain and be non-forgetful of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you just try concentrating and focusing on the ball,
[SPEAKER_00]: As hard, like, really be absorbed in it, as the modern meditation techniques and Theravāda teaches you, you will lose the sight of what's around you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that's kind of exactly... well, for many people that seems like a... like a purpose of the meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is like... it's probably not incidental that... that these practices would be kind of a default of an ignorant mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, although the...
[SPEAKER_00]: The bowl with oil implies the danger of somebody cutting your head off, if you don't forget that there is a man behind you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doubling down and focusing hard on the ball will distract you even from the danger, will make you not feel the danger anymore, because you have been sufficiently self-hypnotized, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why these practices would be popular, because they offer a seeming escape from the problem by really just fortifying your attention away from the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by fixing the danger, not by uprooting the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can go back to the actual Sutta part.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Āgama adds to that, when the monks replied, they said, no, he wouldn't be careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would unify his mind and he would think about a bowl.
[SPEAKER_00]: And among the worldly beautiful form and the great crowd, he wouldn't be daring to glance or look around.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wouldn't be daring to be engaged with it, which would imply forgetting about the ball.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even when the Buddha asked that, even in the Pali Sutra, he says, what do you think, monks, would that man not attend to the old ball and allow negligence outwardly?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Pali says.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, allowing the negligence outwardly, it's what takes you away from
[SPEAKER_00]: From the right balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: What takes you away from the recollectiveness of the body?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you not being focusing hard enough on sensations or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, if you don't choose the negligence, you are staying on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are not spilling the oil.
[SPEAKER_00]: And...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, like, when I ask this question to people,
[SPEAKER_00]: One of the replies was quite interesting, because the person that replied says they actually had to do something similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: They used to work in a Chinese hot pot restaurant and had to carry a bowl of hot oil across the restaurant floor during the working hours, when there are children running around, people getting off the tables and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was like a... and as it happened,
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, like, at that time they were practicing the very typical modern concentration methods and practices going on retreats and similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, while they were carrying the bowl, they actually tried to do the idea of the Buddhist practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they were focusing on the fingers of holding the bowl and on the soles of your feet and mindfully walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And almost instantly, basically, realized that they lost the sight of the danger of spilling the oil on a child's head.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that scared him even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you focus and everything seems fine and calm, and then you just wake up and realize what environment you are still in.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the implications?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on top of it, you obviously probably realize that you haven't been paying attention to the children and what's coming your way as much, because you were so focused on your own sensations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that person said that they pretty much had to decide that while they're working at that place, they'll put the Buddhist practice...
[SPEAKER_00]: They still didn't see the practice of those concentration breaks as a problem, but they realized that they had to put it aside and they can't do it in that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they'll do it when they go back home or something, because it was just incompatible with being aware of your surroundings.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's coming your way and being aware of the danger and the implications of what would happen if you were to actually hurt somebody and cause injuries with that oil.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they said they almost instantly realized that it won't work and all they then did is like they simply
[SPEAKER_00]: People kept reminding themselves, or not being able to forget, not trying to forget, that splashing the oil meant danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Splashing the oil meant consequences.
[SPEAKER_00]: Splashing the old man lawsuits.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this, as I said, like that seemingly abstract context actually became very real and directed all the subsequent actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: How they walked, what they looked at, how they carried the ball, how they lifted the ball, what they thought about, what they planned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything was unified through the recollection of the right context of the danger or any implications of certain actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, yeah, like you could see this example, as I said before, even in the most mundane situations.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's only because, as I said, most of us would have arrived at the suttas and started reading the suttas after you already picked up these views of what meditation is, and the practices, and the ideas, and hopes, and expectations, what will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, we read the suttas or been reading the suttas through that lens, through those kind of tinted glasses, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were to take a non-Buddhist and give them these examples and ask them to do it and then ask them to describe how they would do it,
[SPEAKER_00]: At no point in time would any of them resort to describing sensation watching, hard focusing, intense focus, concentration, where everything else disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, all these contemporary descriptions of what meditation is in jhānas, which is basically just, as we said so many times before, a form of self-hypnosis.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you just
[SPEAKER_00]: Do a little research and see what self-hypnosis is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people, they do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how they do it, it's like verbatim.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just exactly the same practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you might use different terms and labels to it, but you're doing exactly the same thing, which is taking completely the opposite way of where you should be if you follow the example and the simile of the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the context of the danger, they would then guide your actions and your choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly, the level of your engagement with sensuality will also be kept in check.
[SPEAKER_00]: What else can we mention?
[SPEAKER_00]: I did ask that in the past as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like attention and concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, what's the difference between attention and concentration?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, does attention mean concentration, or are you attending things without needing to concentrate on them?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, it's kind of obvious to anybody that's been listening to our talks, but maybe to new people that come to watch this, you could think about it yourself, before you hear what I'm about to answer, and see if you could actually see for yourself what the difference is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when I'm attending to something, I'm not concentrating on something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... as I have said, like, in the earlier talks, like, so, attention is not concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're always attending to something, directly, indirectly, basically, there is always... attention is always resting on something, but that's not concentrating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Concentrating is choosing to to artificially emphasize that which you have already been attending.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... in a way, it's like... concentration is a way of over-attending, which is usually done because you have one or the other reason to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you would have picked up the views that focusing, like beaming down onto the object of your meditation or whatever, is super important because, you know, the whole tradition tells you it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you choose to artificially over-attend something until everything else disappears from your view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like narrowing down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's completely the opposite from surmounting and including and that ekāgatha, that elevation that the suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, in the practice of concentration, for one reason or the other, you choose to single out an idea or an object and then really, like, double down in your ways of attending it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could think of, like, attention does not need concentration, but there is no concentration without attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: And,
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you know, to some degree, dealing with stuff, sometimes you need to attend something more at the expense of something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's already a concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, concentration is not in and of itself inherently bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a... it's like what mind does.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a nature of the experience and to some degree you are attending stuff and I said if you have a reason to do, you would be like increasing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like that it's concentrating is always bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it comes to the practice of the dhamma, where you need to keep that broad picture in the mind, the sense of danger, the implication, implications, the counterpart, the sense objects that are trying to pull you and narrow down your perspective and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like, oh, concentration is actually kind of the tool of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how sensuality works.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it naturally sucks you in, concentrates you, makes you forget about everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It makes you forget what's important to you as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha would often talk about frequently recollecting those topics and perceptions that are important to you as somebody who wants to practice rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And recollection and recollectedness and non-forgetfulness and that memory is not something you can concentrate on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: By unfocusing from things, by unfocusing from the sensations of the top of your head, you become aware of what's already there, the big picture, the rowdy crowd, the need to walk through it, the man behind you with a sword.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, so I shall maintain the practice of unfocusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever my attention, that naturally rests on stuff, starts being sucked in further, either through sensuality or through artificial contemporary concentration meditation practices, I shall unattend to that extent, to stay on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, as the sutra says, the simile, obviously, the equivalent of the ball of oil, is the recollectedness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I described that before, well, many times before, in so many talks, the actual body is not something, as a collection of... the actual body as a saḷāyatana, as basically the sense organs, as a unity, which is your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eyes, nose, ears, sense of touch, tongue, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can't attend your sense organs.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot concentrate on them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot single them out as objects, because they're always negative to its corresponding objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eye can never see itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how hard it tries to look.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply, it's always behind the look.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tongue can never taste itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, obviously, body can never touch itself, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... the actual body that you're mindful of, is not something you can directly attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the saḷāyatana,
[SPEAKER_00]: That the need to be surmounted is not something that appears, that can appear, as an object of your attention and perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's always something indirect, it's always something peripheral, it's always something that can only be known.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, if the body can only be known peripherally, then you realize, okay, so, it's already there,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that I'm not aware of the body if I haven't been focusing or trying to figure it out hard enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like I become unaware of the body when I choose to be negligent towards things outwardly, how the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the virtue that we often talk about and sensory strength outlines the body, outlines the mind for you, outlines the entire domain of four satipaṭṭhānas for the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a practice you can do instead of virtue, instead of withdrawal from the outwardly negligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not... it's not simply not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole point of it is that whether you're making the effort to do it, to figure it out, unless you're withdrawn from the sense objects, unless you are not choosing to go into the crowd and start dancing and singing yourself and looking at the enticing sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless you stop doing those things, you won't be mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how hard you try to outline the body and see it peripherally and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's like, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: But on the other hand, if you are actually stop engaging in the acts of the external negligence, even if you don't make the effort internally to think about, you know, the body and make all this sense out of the things we say, you will be closer to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not, as I said, you're not obstructing it through all these unnecessary external engagements that are rooted in greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like a training in that peripheral recognition of what's already there, the sense of body as experience as a whole, not a specific sensation which is just a sense of touch, because the body is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, training in the peripheral recognition on the basis of virtue and your choice to not follow the enticing sense objects,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you are mindful of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you practice the recollectedness correctly, the non-forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's pretty much, as I said, the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing the danger, the context around you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you won't be able to forget about a bowl full of oil on top of your head, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing the dangers of losing the sight of that peripheral body, of that indirect body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And falling into a trap of... of being... being controlled by the sense objects, whereby you think you're observing your body, but you're just observing just another among the sense objects, it's just like being fully sucked into the central domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the peril.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like the man cutting your head off.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... like, people have asked, like, also, how does the... the... the cutting your head off, how does that translate?
[SPEAKER_00]: That danger, that kind of immediate death, how does that translate to
[SPEAKER_00]: recollectness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it translates to, like, you know, in the other suttas, when the Buddha said, those who are not mindful, who are not recollected here, they are as if dead already.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it translates to, as I just described.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are... you are within the central domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not being recollected properly, on the right level, by being overly focused or overly negligent or overly concentrated due to whatever views you might be carrying about the special meditation experiences and calming you get from it, you are... you're not leaving the central domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're very well and thoroughly still bound by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like being in a car that's flying down a hill, in a bus.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although you're technically still alive, like, you're dead, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no chance of you surviving that situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly what the Buddha meant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those who are not recollected are as if dead already.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like the... Where was it now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the verses that the Buddha adds towards the end in the Yāgama.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a monk who is correct in the body and self-respecting, unifying his mind and thoughts, not giving attention to the sounds and forms, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: sense objects, well-collecting all mental phenomena?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, correct in the body means that, means virtues, means not... having not being engaging in... in things that... in breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Upright.
[SPEAKER_00]: Self-respecting means what we often talk about authentic, transparent, having respect basically for... for your values, for what you know is valuable, not ignoring that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you unify your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which is outlined by being protected, not being distracted from, through your choices of negligence, choosing to not give attention to unsuitable sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, sense objects,
[SPEAKER_00]: You are then the one who is practicing satipaṭṭhāna and subduing the worldly craving and sorrow, as the sutta says, and pretty much developing the right understanding and unobstructing that which prevents you from having the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's again... that's why we insist so many times, like, you know, if you want to practice for the right view, at least, you need to be withdrawn from the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's simply not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you be practicing for the right view while not being subdued, while not subduing the worldly craving and sorrow, while still being very much engaged, controlled by the desires, fears, griefs, passions towards the world and sense objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just two opposite directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have it both ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, the verses that he adds, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It kind of reminds me even of that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I met a sutta where it says like to protect your mind like a mother protects her child.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you have to go through the crowd or go out and do this or that or attend to things,
[SPEAKER_00]: At the back of your mind, the importance of your child being left alone there, unattended, is there, and you will quickly return to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will spend bare minimum of your time elsewhere, because it means danger grows.
[SPEAKER_00]: It increases, because you left the child unattended.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Guard your own mind accordingly, so to reach the place not yet reached.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what all the Buddhas have spoken, the doctrine of a sharp sword, meaning the dhamma is like a sharp sword.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just cuts through the stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: One should unify one's mind, diligently guard it and uphold it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No ordinary man, in the matters of negligence, can enter such a state.
[SPEAKER_00]: The teaching of non-negligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it really... the verse has just boiled down the whole point of the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about negligence and non-negligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not about, you know, concentrated focus on a clay object or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, are you choosing the negligence?
[SPEAKER_00]: And not recognizing the danger implicit in that, or are you recognizing the danger of negligence and not choosing it, not willfully going towards it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, those who choose the non-negligence, they are the ones that can pass into this... through this difficult state and reach deliberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those, they're still very much choosing negligence, regardless of what practices they try to do in order to compensate for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If their actions are still actions of negligence, distraction, lust, aversion, and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: There is simply no room for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't fit through this thin cut that the Buddha's teaching creates, the middle way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think I answered all the points and questions that I got, either directly or indirectly.